{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This state’s Ybor City was a center for cigar manufacturing, and its Hialeah is home to many marielitos and balseros who arrived before the wet foot-dry foot policy was implemented. Elian Gonzalez was deported from this state as a child, an event which is thought to have led many in its large Cuban-American community to turn against Al Gore in the close presidential election in this state in 2000. For ten points, name this US state, some 90 miles north of Cuba.",
      "answer": "Florida A"
    },
    {
      "question": "Francis Walsingham used this woman’s correspondence with Anthony Babington to convict her of treason. Shortly before her execution, this woman embroidered the motto “In my End is my Beginning” on her cloth of estate. After this woman’s third marriage, Protestant nobles forced her surrender at the Battle of Carberry. The Casket Letters were produced by the Earl of Moray as an attempt to prove this woman’s involvement in Lord Darnley’s murder. For ten points, name this queen of Scotland, the mother of James I of England.",
      "answer": [
        "Mary, Queen of Scots",
        "Mary Stuart",
        "Mary I of Scotland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This colony gained independence after talks with Patrice Lumumba and Moise Tshombe led to Joseph DKasavubu becoming its first president. A hundred years earlier, this colony was explored and subsequently claimed by Henry Morgan Stanley. The Casement Report detailed atrocities carried out in this colony by the Force Publique, which utilized forced labor in harvesting rubber. For ten points, name this colony once privately controlled by King Leopold II of Belgium.",
      "answer": [
        "Belgian Congo",
        "Congo Free State",
        "Democratic Republic of the Congo,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In one battle, this city was defended by a floating chain placed on logs to impede ship movement. An emperor legendarily turned into marble after the fall of this city, which was assaulted by the massive Dardanelles gun built by Orban. This city was protected by the walls of the Golden Horn and defenders utilizing Greek Fire. This city lost control of the Bosphorus prior to its fall to Mehmed II in 1453. For ten points, what capital of the Byzantines fell to the Ottoman Empire?",
      "answer": [
        "Constantinople",
        "Istanbul",
        "Byzantium T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After 1885, this natural formation was named for a New York lawyer and prospector, but its original LakotaSiouxnamemeans“SixGrandfathers.”HistorianDoaneRobinson’soriginalplanforthisformation included Red Cloud, Meriwether Lewis, William Clark, and “Buffalo Bill” Cody. Its sculptor, Gutzon Borglum, thought this formation needed to appeal to a broader audience and chose four other subjects. F For ten points, what is this National Memorial in the Black Hills of South Dakota, featuring the faces of four U.S. presidents?",
      "answer": "Mount Rushmore"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Viscount Rothermere founded a business of this type that advertised as being “for office boys.” One of these companies claimed that a missile it photographed was poised to hit “Galtieri’s gauchos.” During the Winter of Discontent that business of this type popularized the phrase “Crisis? What Crisis?” A and is one of several of them owned by Rupert Murdoch. For ten points, name these businesses that include The Sun and the London Times.",
      "answer": "Newspapers"
    },
    {
      "question": "Support for this event gained traction when Albert Wedemeyer was able to apply his experiences traveling from India to China via the Himalayas. Logistics for this event were supplied by Brian Robertson to General Lucius Clay. Gail Halvorsen became known as the “candy bomber” during this event, the U.S. portion of which was codenamed Operation Vittles. 4,500 tons of cargo were delivered daily at this event’s heiRght. For ten points, name this 1948 event in which the Western Allies circumvented a Soviet blockade in Germany.",
      "answer": "Berlin Airlift"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Isabel Allende’s novel Daughter of Fortune, one of these events causes Joaquin to leave a pregnant Eliza. A Skookum king offers over $1000 gained from one of these events to buy a character that is mistreated by Hal, Charles, and Mercedes before befriending John Thornton. That character, Buck, appears in the Jack London novel The Call of the Wild, which is set against the backdrop of one of these Devents in the Yukon. For ten points, name these events, a famous example of which saw miners flock to California in 1849.",
      "answer": "Gold rush"
    },
    {
      "question": "Kate Smith debuted a modified version of this song during the 1938 Armistice Day broadcast of her radio show. To avoid political undertones, this song’s lyrics “to the right” were changed to “through the night.” Woody Guthrie wrote “This Land Is Your Land” in direct response to this song that describes a light shining “from the mountains, to the prairies.” This song urges the listener to “stand beside” and “guide” the central land. Ending by calling the title country “My home sweet home,” For ten points, name this patriotic song by Irving Berlin.",
      "answer": "“God Bless America” T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following this event, a New York merchant named Robert Murray offered compensation to its victims but was refused. This event legendarily began with thFe codewords “this meeting can do nothing more to save our country” after Thomas Hutchinson refused to allow the Dartmouth to leave. This event helped contribute to the Intolerable Acts and the closing of a certain harbor. For ten points, name this event in which colonists dressed up as Mohawks and destroyed crates of Darjeeling.",
        "answer": "Boston Tea Party"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the least-liked provisions within the Intolerable acts was this act that required families to house soldiers. A",
        "answer": "Quartering Act"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A king of this name became the final monarch to dismiss an English prime minister when he removed Lord Melbourne. Child labour was banned during the reign of a king of this name, the last of the Hanoverian dynasty. A king of this name took power when his predecessor’s Declaration of Indulgence led to that man’s overthrow. Rotten boroughs were eliminated in an attempt to expand votership when the “Great Reform Bill” was passed under a king of this name. For ten points, the Catholic James II was overthrown by a king of what name during the Glorious Revolution? R",
        "answer": "William"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "If Prince William, the grandson of Elizabeth II and current Duke of Cambridge, succeeds to the British throne, what will be his regnal number as King William?",
        "answer": "Five or Fifth"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One company in this industry, prior to merging with Mo¨et et Chandon and Hennesy, had made products named Speedy and Noe. The founder of another company in this industry worked with Arthur D “Boy” Capel and created a “uniform for afternoon and evening” known as that founder’s namesake suit. That company made a famous number 5 product and was influenced by the “New Look” of Christian Dior. “The Little Black Dress” style comes from, for ten points, what industry whose companies include Louis Vuitton and Chanel?",
        "answer": "Fashion Industry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Louis Vuitton himself was the personal trunk maker and packer for Eugenie de Montijo, the wife of Napoleon III, and, as such, the last woman to hold this title.",
        "answer": "Empress of France T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This son of the Younger Lady may have died as a result of birth defects, though other theories include sickle cell anemia and a blow to the head. This man reversed the religious policies of his father Akhenaten and rejected Aten in favor of Amun-Re. In 1922, this man’s tomb was discovered by Harold Carter in the Valley of the Kings. For ten points, name this boy pharaoh whose tomb is the subject of a namesake curse. F",
        "answer": [
          "Tutankhamun",
          "King Tut"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Perhaps the best known piece of King Tut’s treasure is this piece, 21 inches tall and weighing 23 pounds, topped by a cobra and vulture and inlaid with lapis lazuli, obsidian, and a variety of other stones.",
        "answer": [
          "Mask",
          "any answer that indicates a covering of the face of Tutankhamun"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Martin Fernandez De EAncisco is credited with being the first European to write about this particular food, an undomesticated variety of which is known as its criollo variant. The most popular variety in the world is named after the man who developed the variety in California, Rudolf Hass. The U.S. lifted a ban on imports of this fruit during the 1990s, and the consumption of this single-seeded berry has tripled on Super Bowl Sundays due to its use in a popular dip. For ten points, name this green fruit used to make guacamole.",
        "answer": [
          "Avocado pear",
          "Alligator pear",
          "Persea americana"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The avocado likely originated in the Tehuacan Valley in the state of Puebla in this country. R",
        "answer": [
          "Mexico",
          "United Mexican States, UMS, Estados Unidos Mexicanos,",
          "EUM"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, one fleeing perpetrator attempted to jump into the Miljacka [meel-YOCK-ah] river only to find it was less than a foot deep. This event was planned by a man named “Apis” and later coordinated by Danilo Ilic [EE-litch]. One of the victims of this event was the commoner Sophie Chotek, whom this event’s intended target told to “live for our children” before he was killed by the Black Hand. Gavrilo Princip carried out, for ten points, what 1914 assassination that sparked World War One? DANSWER: Assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand (accept any answer that indicates the killing of Franz Ferdinand) BONUS: Franz Ferdinand was the son of Emperor Franz Joseph I of this empire.",
        "answer": "Austro-Hungarian Empire 7 In one play by this author, he describes a “band of brothers” in the St. Crispin’s Day Speech, delivered by a royal character shortly before the Battle of Agincourt. Another of this writer’s plays has characters based on Holinshed’s Chronicles and is considered cursed in theatre circles. This husband of Anne Hathaway and resident of Stratford-upon-Avon premiered many of his works at the Globe Theatre. For ten points, name this Elizabethan-era playwright of Henry V, Macbeth, and Hamlet. ANSWER: William Shakespeare"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shakespeare’s final History Play and his only play about a Tudor king is what 1613 work, responsible for the burning of the Globe after a cannon ignited its thatched roof?",
        "answer": [
          "Henry VIII",
          "All is True T"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This contemporary denomination of currency originated as the lowest valued member of the “seven-thirty” Interest Bearing Notes issued during the Civil War. Edward Everett and Silas Wright were among the men whose faces were on certificates bearing the value of this bill. After the $2 bill, this is the second-least commonly circulated bill of U.S. currency. Today, these bills depict a president who had to F deal with the Whiskey Ring Scandal and the Panic of 1873. For ten points, name this U.S. paper currency which includes a portrait of the eighteenth president, Ulysses Grant.",
        "answer": "United States fifty-dollar bill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The reverse of the fifty-dollar bill depicts this neoclassical building, originally completed in 1800 and located at the eastern end of the National Mall.",
        "answer": "United States Capitol Building A"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The U.S. Civil War",
      "prompt": "In the U.S. Civil War, who or what was the:",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American president who issued the Emancipation Proclamation? F",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederate general from Virginia who surrendered at Appomattox Courthouse?",
          "answer": "Robert E Lee"
        },
        {
          "question": "South Carolina fort whose siege marked the start of the war?",
          "answer": "Fort Sumter A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederate general who earned his nickname with a valiant defense at First Bull Run?",
          "answer": "Thomas “Stonewall” Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fortress city in Mississippi sieged by the Union in 1863?",
          "answer": "Vicksburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle in Tennessee with vicious fighting at “The Hornet’s Nest”?",
          "answer": [
            "Shiloh",
            "Pittsburg Landing R"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Virginia siege at which the USCT fought valiantly at the Battle of the Crater?",
          "answer": "Petersburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Angel of the Battlefield” who went on to found the American Red Cross?",
          "answer": "Clara Barton D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Soviet space program",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First man in space who orbited the Earth aboard Vostok 1 in 1961 F",
          "answer": "Yuri Gagarin"
        },
        {
          "question": "First satellite, launched in 1957",
          "answer": "Sputnik 1"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet premier who began de-Stalinization and supported the early space program",
          "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of spacecraft used in a joint spaceflight with the American Apollo program",
          "answer": "Soyuz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Present-day Central Asian country with capital Nur-Sultan from which missions were launched",
          "answer": "Republic of Kazakhstan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Title for Soviet astronauts from the words for “universe” and “explorer”",
          "answer": "Cosmonaut R"
        },
        {
          "question": "First woman in space, the pilot of Vostok 6",
          "answer": "Valentina Tereshkova"
        },
        {
          "question": "Space station launched in 1986 whose name translates to “peace”",
          "answer": "Mir D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Coup d’etats",
      "prompt": "Name the nation from a description of the coup...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "In 1999, Nawaz Sharif was overthrown by General Pervez Musharraf. F",
          "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1992, Carlos Andres Perez held power against a coup led by Hugo Chavez.",
          "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "The 23-F incident in 1981 was squelched by King Juan Carlos.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Spain A"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1940, after the German invasion, a coup attempt was made by Vidkun Quisling.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Norway"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Sergeants’ Revolt of 1933 propelled Fulgencio Batista to power.",
          "answer": "Republic of Cuba"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1953, U.S. and British intelligence overthrew Mohammed Mosaddegh.",
          "answer": "Imperial State of Iran R"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1970, Prince Sihanouk was overthrown by Prime Minister Lon Nol.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Cambodia"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1971, Milton Obote was overthrown by army chief Idi Amin.",
          "answer": "Republic of Uganda D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1985, this company purchased Hughes Aircraft and merged it with Delco Electronics. Alfred Sloan began the practice of positioFning brands of this company to specific socioeconomic demographics. A 1937 sit-down strike launched by the (20 pts)",
        "UAW was ended when this company came to an agreement with its workers. William Durant founded this company, who launched a failed campaign to buy out (10 pts)",
        "Ford. Founded in Flint, Michigan, for ten points, name this American car manufacturer whose brands include Buick and Chevrolet."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "General Motors",
        "GM"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After a defeat in this war’s Battle of Worcester, a man who was later restored as king A of his country escaped pursuit by hiding in the Royal Oak. The cavalry of Prince Rupert proved decisive in the victory of one side in this war at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Edgehill, but he was soundly defeated at the Battle of Marston Moor. With the victory of the New Model Army at the Battle of Naseby, the (10 pts)",
        "Roundheads defeated the Royalist Cavaliers to win the first phase of this war. For ten points, name this 17th-century war that ended in the victory of the Parliamentarian forces of Oliver Cromwell."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "English Civil War 3RMany refugees who were forced to flee this city often refer to its capture as “Black April”",
        "“National Day of Resentment.” “Operation Cedar Falls” was meant to clear out the + Iron Triangle centered around this city. This city was left exposed after the battle of Xuan Loc. Task Force 76 was formed to execute Operation Frequent Wind in this city, the largest * helicopter evacuation in history, as it fell to the Viet Minh in 1975. For ten points, name this capital of South Vietnam. ANSWER: Saigon",
        "Ho Chi Minh City D"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this war’s first major land battle, the Eastern Detachment was defeated at the village of Wiju. Two days after this war, an exploding magazine inadvertently destroyed the Mikasa, the flagship that began this war by launching a surprise attack on (20 pts)",
        "Port Arthur. Theodore Roosevelt won a Nobel Peace Prize for his help ending this war through the Treaty of (10 pts)",
        "Portsmouth after one side’s Baltic Fleet was defeated at Tsushima Straits. For ten points, name this war in which Meiji Japan humiliated a Western empire led by Nicholas II."
      ],
      "answer": "Russo-Japanese War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the Second World War, this astronaut served as a gunner on the Cogswell during the Battle of Okinawa. As a 47-year old, this man became the oldest man to ever walk on the (20 pts)",
        "moon as commander of Apollo 14, in which capacity he was the first man to hit a golf ball in space. This man nearly broke his hand in anger after Yuri Gagarin was sent to space a (10 pts)",
        "month before this man took off in Freedom 7, the first manned mission of Project Mercury. For ten points, name this first American in space."
      ],
      "answer": "Alan Shepard T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler ignited one rebellion after appointing Yuri Dolgoruki to round up fugitive peasants in lands that were led by Kondraty Bulavin. This ruler signed the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Constantinople with Mustafa II, which led to this ruler creating his country’s first naval base at Taganrog. This ruler instituted a Beard Tax for (10 pts)",
        "Boyars after he traveled incognito F to observe a Dutch shipyard as part of his Grand Embassy. For ten points, name this Tsar whose reforms modernized 18th century Russia."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Peter I",
        "Peter the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After Zadok anointed this man as king, Nathan blessed him by giving him the name Jedidiah. Adonijah [ad-uh-NIE-jah], this man’s half brother, attempted to organize a coup d’etat against him by requesting to marry (20 pts)",
        "Abishag. This leader reprimanded the Queen A of Sheba for lifting her skirt and revealing her hairy legs, and this man took on foreign idols due to marrying (10 pts)",
        "more than 300 wives from many lands. For ten points, name this son of David, known for building the First Temple in Jerusalem and considered the wisest man in the Old Testament."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Solomon",
        "Shlomoh,",
        "Jedidiah before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Five months after an event in this city, a court case inspired by it, Cooper v. Aaron, ruled that states must enforce all Supreme Court decisions regardless of their attitude toward them. Melba Beals and Ernest Green were among the central figures involved in thaRt event in this city, during which (20 pts)",
        "Orval Faubus attempted to thwart the central group. Dwight Eisenhower called the 101st Airborn Division to this city to escort a group of (10 pts)",
        "students to their classes. For ten points, name this city, where nine African-American students tried to enroll in the segregated Central High School."
      ],
      "answer": "Little Rock, Arkansas"
    }
  ]
}